Guide to the Jus Addiss and Hayden Rorke "This is the Army" Travel Photographs, 1944-1945 PR 462
New-York Historical Society
Jus Addiss and Hayden Rorke "This is the Army" travel photographs
1944-1945
New-York Historical Society
Addiss, Jus, 1917-1979.
Rorke, Hayden, 1910-1987.
PR 462
0.209 Linear feet in 1 half-document box (139 black-and-white photographs measuring between 3x5 and 4x6 inches)
Photographs by and of Justus "Jus" Addiss (1917–1979) and Hayden Rorke (1910–1987), taken during their time in the U.S. military, while they toured in the Irving Berlin musical "This is the Army," which was performed at Allied bases in Europe, the Middle East, and the Pacific during World War II. Addiss later became a well-known director of television programs ("Rawhide" and "Voyage to the Bottom of the Sea."). Rorke is best remembered for his role as NASA psychiatrist Dr. Bellows in the 1960s sitcom "I Dream of Jeannie." Rorke and Addiss were romantic partners who lived together until the latter's death in 1979.
Access Restrictions
This collection is stored offsite. To arrange to view it, please go to www.nyhistory.org/library/visit.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Gail and James Addiss, 2023 (accession no. PPAC-2023-023).
Arrangement
The collection is organized chronologically.
Historical note
"This is the Army" was a World War II-era American musical (book by James McColl, music and lyrics by Irving Berlin) that was produced by the U.S. Army on Broadway over twelve weeks in the summer of 1942. During its run at the Broadway Theatre, the show—starring soldiers alongside professional performers and featuring such memorable tunes as "Oh! How I Hate to Get Up in the Morning"—raised $40,000 per week for the benefit of the Army Emergency Relief Fund. It next toured nationally and internationally, and in 1943 became a musical comedy film by the same title. In 1944–1945, under the auspices of the Special Services branch of the American military, the production traveled to Allied bases in Europe, the Middle East, and the Pacific, bringing along much of the same cast to entertain troops stationed there. The final performance of "This is the Army" took place on Maui, Hawaii, on October 22, 1945.
Two men associated with the show—and long associated with each other—were Justus "Jus" Addiss (1917–1979) and Hayden Rorke (1910–1987). Addiss served as stage manager for the touring productions of "This is the Army." He went on to a career directing television programs such as "The Twilight Zone" and "Mr. Ed." Hayden Rorke (born William Henry Rorke) was a prolific actor who appeared in the Broadway run of "This is the Army," and made his screen debut (uncredited) in the film version. He is best remembered for playing Colonel Alfred Bellows in the 1960s sitcom "I Dream of Jeannie." Rorke and Addiss were romantic partners who lived together until the latter's death in 1979.
Related Materials
The New-York Historical Society also holds the Jack Sydow Papers and Photographs (PR 289). Sydow was an actor, director, and playwright who wrote and performed in several variety shows while in the military during World War II. His "Hump Happy," in which he starred with fellow service members, was the first such production to travel across combat areas, with productions at bases in Africa, India, and the Middle East.
Scope and Contents
This collection contains 139 photographs by and of Justus "Jus" Addiss (1917–1979) and Hayden Rorke (1910–1987), taken during their time in the U.S. military during World War II, while they were touring with the Special Service Division in the Irving Berlin musical "This is the Army." Each print bears a handwritten or typed caption on the back, identifying the places and people appearing in the view. Locations include Italy (May-July 1944), Egypt (August 1944), the Holy Land (August 1944), Iran (October 1944), India (November 1944), and the Philippines (March and May, 1945). (Refer to the container list for more specific location information.)
While the musical production itself is not represented by photographs, the collection does include some views of the stage under construction and completed (taken in the Philippines; see Folder 8), and of the dressing room (taken in Persia [Iran]; see Folder 6). And, along with Addiss and Rorke—who is identified by "Bill," as his birth name was William—a number of other men appear in the photographs, most of whom were fellow servicemen and performers. Some are fully named; others are identified only by their first names or nicknames. Many are listed in the Broadway and film credits of "This is the Army":
• "Alan"
• Allon Trio (or Flying Allon Trio): Angelo "Angie" Buono (1913–1996), Louis Bednarcik (1917–2008), and Geno Erbisti (1911–1974)
• "Art"
• Leander Eugene "Gene" Berg [a.k.a. Gene Nelson] (1920–1996)
• Irving Berlin (1888–1989)
• "Bert"
• Joe Bush
• Carl Fisher (1909–1974)
• "Gilmour"
• Alan Holmes
• Philip "Phil" Jones
• "Marcus"
• Ralph Magelssen (1909–1989)
• Jules "Julie" Oshins (1906–1956)
• Anthony "Tony" Ross (1906–1955)
• Frank Scadden
• "Washer"
• Cass Yaeger [possibly Casse Jaeger (1915–1996)]
Bari (Italy) -- Photographs.; Batangas (Philippines) -- Photographs.; Cairo (Egypt) -- Photographs.; Foggia (Italy) -- Photographs.; Iran -- Photographs.; Israel -- Photographs.; Jerusalem -- Photographs.; Jīzah (Egypt) -- Photographs.; Manila (Philippines) -- Photographs.; Mumbai (India) -- Photographs.; Palestine -- Photographs.; Rome (Italy) -- Photographs.; Black-and-white photographs.; Gay actors.; Gay men -- United States.; Gay military personnel -- United States.; Military morale.; Musicals.; World War, 1939-1945 -- Photographs.; Addiss, Jus, 1917-1979.; Berlin, Irving, 1888-1989. -- This is the Army.; Rorke, Hayden, 1910-1987.; United States. Army Service Forces. Special Service Division
- Addiss and Rorke photographs: Italy, 1944 May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 1)
  Scope and Contents
  12 photographs taken in "Santa Maria, Italy." This was likely Santa Maria Capua Vetere, in Caserta, Campania, given the presence of its "Colosseum," properly known as the Amphitheatre of Capua, and considered to be the probable model for the Colosseum in Rome.
- Addiss and Rorke photographs: Italy, 1944 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 2)
  13 photographs taken in Foggia and Rome, including views of the Forum, St. Peter's Basilica, and St. John Lateran.
- Addiss and Rorke photographs: Italy, 1944 July (Offsite-box 1, Folder 3)
  8 photographs taken in Foggia and Bari.
- Addiss and Rorke photographs: Egypt, 1944 August 20 (Offsite-box 1, Folder 4)
  13 photographs of the Great Sphinx and pyramids of Giza, and the Cairo Opera House.
- Addiss and Rorke photographs: Holy Land, 1944 August (Offsite-box 1, Folder 5)
  26 photographs taken in Bethlehem, Jerusalem, and Tel Aviv. Sites include the Mount of Olives (Bethlehem); Church of the Nativity, Via Dolorosa (or Stations of the Cross), and the Wailing Wall (Jerusalem).
- Addiss and Rorke photographs: Persia (Iran), 1944 October (Offsite-box 1, Folder 6)
  18 photographs taken in the cities of Ahwaz, Arak, Dizful, "Hamandau" (Hamadan?), Kazvin (Qazvin), "Khoranshahr" (Khorramshahr?), and "Teheran" (Tehran). Includes a view of the typical dressing room for "This is the Army."
- Addiss and Rorke photographs: India, 1944 November (Offsite-box 1, Folder 7)
  6 photographs taken in Bombay (now Mumbai).
- Addiss and Rorke photographs: Philippines, 1945 March (Offsite-box 1, Folder 8)
  15 photographs taken in the Philippines. Includes views of the Catholic Church of Liberation, Church of the Immaculate Conception, and of the stage for "This is the Army" under construction and completed.
- Addiss and Rorke photographs: Philippines, 1945 May (Offsite-box 1, Folder 9)
  25 photographs taken in Batangas and Manila, showing the wreckage of the bombardment of Manila.
- Addiss and Rorke photographs: At sea, 1945 June (Offsite-box 1, Folder 10)
  3 photographs of Addiss and Rorke aboard ship.
- Addiss and Rorke photographs: Miscellaneous (4 items) (Offsite-box 1, Folder 11)
  (1) Blank envelope stamped with the return address of "Edward F. Addiss, 100 East 42nd Street, New York 17, N.Y."
  (2) Envelope sent from "E. F. Addiss, 100 East 42nd Street, New York 17, N.Y.," to "Mrs. Francis J. Addiss, 121 South Street, Jersey City, New Jersey," postmarked 19 February 1945. Originally held photographs of "Bombay, India," now in Folder 7.
  (3) Envelope that originally held the photographs of "Jerusalem, etc." and "Egypt and the Holy Land" now in Folders 4 and 5.
  (4) Postcard of Mount Fuji, Japan, postmarked 24 April [1973?], mailed to "Mrs. Joseph [Gertrude] Munafo, 530 East 23rd Street, New York, New York 10010," signed "Bill and Jus."